<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Matteo's Website - Anime</title><link href="https:/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https:///feeds/anime.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https:/</id><updated>2023-04-20T00:00:00-04:00</updated><entry><title>Look, I'm Just Going To Say It</title><link href="https:///look-im-just-going-to-say-it.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2023-04-20T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2023-04-20T00:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Matteo Raso</name></author><id>tag:None,2023-04-20:/look-im-just-going-to-say-it.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;"Neon Genesis Evangelion" was mid. I enjoyed it, and I certainly didn't regret watching it, but it's not the groundbreaking anime that everybody seems to think that it is. It's just a normal mecha with slightly deep themes. The plot was convoluted and a lot of questions get left unanswered …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;"Neon Genesis Evangelion" was mid. I enjoyed it, and I certainly didn't regret watching it, but it's not the groundbreaking anime that everybody seems to think that it is. It's just a normal mecha with slightly deep themes. The plot was convoluted and a lot of questions get left unanswered, which gives a lot of room for fan discussion but ultimately just made it a pain to watch at times. The ending was actually fantastic and redeemed the entire show for me, but then the studio decided to undermine that with a series of movies designed to please the fans that hated the ending. To be fair, I've heard that EoE was really good, but I've also heard a lot of bad things about Rebuild. I'll probably do a review of EoE one day, but that still doesn't change the fact that the original anime was underwhelming compared to its reputation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Oh, and it's super creepy how the fanbase is obsessed with discussing which 14 year old is hotter. Even if I was a hardcore fan, I would shy away from revealing that just because the fanbase is seriously that obsessed and I wouldn't want people to think that of me.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Anime"></category></entry></feed>