<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Matteo's Website - Draughts</title><link href="https:/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https:///feeds/draughts.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https:/</id><updated>2023-06-02T00:00:00-04:00</updated><entry><title>Draughts Is Great</title><link href="https:///draughts-is-great.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2023-06-02T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2023-06-02T00:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Matteo Raso</name></author><id>tag:None,2023-06-02:/draughts-is-great.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I've noticed that a lot of posts I make here tend to be negative, so
I decided to write about something that I like. If you don't know,
Draughts is a family of games centred around diagonally moving pieces.
If that sounds like Checkers, that's because Checkers is just an …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I've noticed that a lot of posts I make here tend to be negative, so
I decided to write about something that I like. If you don't know,
Draughts is a family of games centred around diagonally moving pieces.
If that sounds like Checkers, that's because Checkers is just an
American/English form of Draughts. Draughts tends to be misjudged
as Chess for people who aren't smart enough for Chess, but that
assumes that Draughts is supposed to be like Chess in the first place.
In reality, they're different games with different strategies.
Chess requires you to look at a broad array of potential moves,
while Draughts requires you to look deeply into the possible lines
that are available. The main feature of Draughts games is the way
you're forced to make captures. While you're sometimes forced to make
moves in Chess, Draughts will routinely have you finding yourself 
in a position where you're helplessly forced to make bad move after
bad move while a more skilled player prepares a devastating attack
that'll destroy your position. It's great fun, give it a try.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Draughts"></category></entry></feed>