<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Matteo's Website - Misc</title><link href="https:/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https:///feeds/misc.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https:/</id><updated>2023-06-26T00:00:00-04:00</updated><entry><title>Fire</title><link href="https:///fire.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2023-06-26T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2023-06-26T00:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Matteo Raso</name></author><id>tag:None,2023-06-26:/fire.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Yesterday, I went on the shortest walk I've been on in months. The smoke from
the forest fires not too far from my town was extremely bad, so my eyes began
to burn after just a few minutes outside. Growing up, I assumed that we
would have figured out global …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Yesterday, I went on the shortest walk I've been on in months. The smoke from
the forest fires not too far from my town was extremely bad, so my eyes began
to burn after just a few minutes outside. Growing up, I assumed that we
would have figured out global warming before it really began to affect us,
but that clearly didn't happen, and now we have massive forest fires because
everything is too hot. I hope this will be the wakeup call everybody needs
before things get even worse, but I doubt it.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Misc"></category></entry><entry><title>Why Does Mr Beast Do This?</title><link href="https:///why-does-mr-beast-do-this.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2023-06-11T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2023-06-11T00:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Matteo Raso</name></author><id>tag:None,2023-06-11:/why-does-mr-beast-do-this.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;While I was watching yesterday's &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=48h57PspBec"&gt;MrBeast video&lt;/a&gt;, I noticed that the picture from Chris's coming out tweet was taken while filming for the $1,000,000 yacht. That tweet came out April 27, so MrBeast waited over a month to upload this video. I know that you need to edit …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;While I was watching yesterday's &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=48h57PspBec"&gt;MrBeast video&lt;/a&gt;, I noticed that the picture from Chris's coming out tweet was taken while filming for the $1,000,000 yacht. That tweet came out April 27, so MrBeast waited over a month to upload this video. I know that you need to edit and all that, but does it seriously take that long? I wouldn't make a post about this, if it weren't for that fact that he announced the release of his "biggest burger" video for Feastable customers, when he mentioned having that video already in his &lt;a href="https://youtu.be/7IKab3HcfFk?t=585"&gt;Antarctica video&lt;/a&gt;. Far be it from me to question how the biggest Youtuber handles Youtube, but I just found that a little strange.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Misc"></category></entry><entry><title>A Weird Detail I Noticed</title><link href="https:///a-weird-detail-i-noticed.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2023-05-29T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2023-05-29T00:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Matteo Raso</name></author><id>tag:None,2023-05-29:/a-weird-detail-i-noticed.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I entered &lt;a href="https://www.kaggle.com/competitions/playground-series-s3e16/rules"&gt;a Kaggle competition&lt;/a&gt;, and I noticed that nobody from Crimea, the Donetsk People's Republic, or the Luhansk People's Republic was allowed to enter. This is obviously part of the sanctions over the Russo-Ukrainian war, but they don't actually ban Russian residents from entering. What was the point of …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I entered &lt;a href="https://www.kaggle.com/competitions/playground-series-s3e16/rules"&gt;a Kaggle competition&lt;/a&gt;, and I noticed that nobody from Crimea, the Donetsk People's Republic, or the Luhansk People's Republic was allowed to enter. This is obviously part of the sanctions over the Russo-Ukrainian war, but they don't actually ban Russian residents from entering. What was the point of banning the residents of occupied areas but not residents of the occupying country? That's all I wanted to say, there wasn't really a bigger point to this blog post. &lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Misc"></category></entry><entry><title>I Hate The Tiktokification Of The Internet</title><link href="https:///i-hate-the-tiktokification-of-the-internet.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2023-05-27T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2023-05-27T00:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Matteo Raso</name></author><id>tag:None,2023-05-27:/i-hate-the-tiktokification-of-the-internet.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I think Tiktok was one of the worst things to happen to the internet.
Social media and the like have always been bad for you, but short form
content like literally everything found on Tiktok is like cyanide for
your attention span. I refuse to use the app, but it's …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I think Tiktok was one of the worst things to happen to the internet.
Social media and the like have always been bad for you, but short form
content like literally everything found on Tiktok is like cyanide for
your attention span. I refuse to use the app, but it's hard to avoid
the problems of Tiktok when the internet is being consumed by Tiktok.
This isn't Tiktok's fault, they're just running their own app, but 
it's hard to ignore how the content that originates on Tiktok spreads.
Just about every video-sharing website (including websites you don't
normally think of as video-sharing websites, like Reddit and Facebook)
has been flooded with mirrors of Tiktok videos. These videos tend to
be the ones that blow up the most, because short-form content is the
most addictive, creating a feedback loop where people only look for
videos that match Tiktok's short-form style. Youtube is awful for this,
since it shoves Youtube Shorts down your throat. I try to block them,
but Youtube won't let you, since they know these videos are the ones
that keep you glued to the website. I know some people have the
self-control to avoid clicking on any of them, but I don't. I know that
there needs to be personal responsibility and all that, but you
can't tell people to exercise personal responsibility when websites
literally go out of their way to make it difficult for you to block
addictive content. I might just cut Youtube out of my life, honestly.
I've already deleted accounts for a lot of social media sites, and
while it can be pretty boring without a dripfeed of content at all
hours, I don't think a more boring life is a worse one.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Misc"></category></entry><entry><title>When Adding A Recovery Option Makes Things Worse</title><link href="https:///when-adding-a-recovery-option-makes-things-worse.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2023-05-05T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2023-05-05T00:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Matteo Raso</name></author><id>tag:None,2023-05-05:/when-adding-a-recovery-option-makes-things-worse.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;A couple of years ago, I added a recovery phone number to my gmail 
so that I could get into my account if I ever forgot my password.
Fast forward to the present day, and I need to get back into the 
account. Even though I have my password after …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;A couple of years ago, I added a recovery phone number to my gmail 
so that I could get into my account if I ever forgot my password.
Fast forward to the present day, and I need to get back into the 
account. Even though I have my password after all these years, I
couldn't get in without a verification code sent to my old phone
number, which I no longer had. I was able to get my account back
by contacting my old phone number, but that was pure luck. I don't
know why somebody would come up with such a horrible anti-pattern,
but don't do this if you're in charge of a website and you want to
give your user an option to add a recovery phone number. Seriously,
there's no reason to think that somebody coming back to an account
after a few years is suspicious, unless you have a good reason to
think that your company was hacked. Pro-tip, you can keep your users's
passwords from getting cracked if you enforce a reasonable password
policy. That way, you can keep your users safe without locking them
out of their account. I'll never get how Google doesn't understand this.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Misc"></category></entry><entry><title>Hello, World!</title><link href="https:///hello-world.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2023-03-27T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2023-03-27T00:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Matteo Raso</name></author><id>tag:None,2023-03-27:/hello-world.html</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;This is the first post for my new and improved website (there was an old one, but it was garbage). Not sure what I'll be posting here, probably mostly updates on any projects I'm working on.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Misc"></category></entry></feed>