<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Matteo's Website - Video Games</title><link href="https:/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https:///feeds/video-games.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https:/</id><updated>2023-06-21T00:00:00-04:00</updated><entry><title>The Tragedy Of Mobile Gaming</title><link href="https:///the-tragedy-of-mobile-gaming.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2023-06-21T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2023-06-21T00:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Matteo Raso</name></author><id>tag:None,2023-06-21:/the-tragedy-of-mobile-gaming.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I was taking a look at my old GBA, and I couldn't help but think about how
much technology has advanced since it came out. It's been 20 years since that
came out, so according to Moore's Law, modern hardware is 1024x better now.
Seriously, our phones are better than …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I was taking a look at my old GBA, and I couldn't help but think about how
much technology has advanced since it came out. It's been 20 years since that
came out, so according to Moore's Law, modern hardware is 1024x better now.
Seriously, our phones are better than our computers from just a decade ago.
If that's the case, why has mobile gaming been so awful? I know nostalgia is
a huge factor for why I look so fondly at the GBA, but mobile gaming being
an absolute garbage fire is a very common opinion, and with good reason.
Most mobile games (at least the successful ones) are more focused on increasing
metrics like retention and downloads instead of actually being fun, with
profits coming from actively ruining the player experience by shoving ads
down your throats or literally making you addicted through in-game gambling.
It's such a shame that an avenue for gaming that's over 1000 times as strong
as the GBA is being put to waste like this.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Video Games"></category></entry><entry><title>Why I Don't Like Minecraft's Cave Update</title><link href="https:///why-i-dont-like-minecrafts-cave-update.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2023-05-17T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2023-05-17T00:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Matteo Raso</name></author><id>tag:None,2023-05-17:/why-i-dont-like-minecrafts-cave-update.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;As I get back into Minecraft, I'm reminded by how awesome the cliff update
was. It's genuinely breathtaking to see the new overworld terrain generation
while exploring my world. Sadly, I've found myself in a situation where I
have to be reminded that the cliff update was paired with a …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;As I get back into Minecraft, I'm reminded by how awesome the cliff update
was. It's genuinely breathtaking to see the new overworld terrain generation
while exploring my world. Sadly, I've found myself in a situation where I
have to be reminded that the cliff update was paired with a cave update.
I can understand why people (maybe even most people) would like the cave
update, but it's caused me nothing but grief. I have a horrible sense of
direction, so bad that I struggled to navigate caves with the old world
generation. Now that caves are massive, trying to not get lost is pointless.
Instead, I minimize the amount of mining that I need to do by using automatic
farms that get me the things that I need. Still, I do sometimes have to go
mining, so I dig quarries. This was hard enough back in the good old days,
but at least you would only have to deal with fairly small pockets of space
beneath your feet. Now, you have to deal with a massive cavern that you're
going to drop into. When you've dug up all the upper part of the quarry, you
either have to leave the quarry unfinished, or you have to jump into the
cavern and finish it while mobs surround you. I have actual, clinical OCD,
so leaving it unfinished isn't an option for me. That means jumping in, mining,
and desperately trying to find a way out. Like I said, you're in a massive
cavern, so you can't climb up the walls with a bucket of water anymore. You
can leave a stream of water running from the top of the quarry, but that'll
make it hard to mine. Like I said, I don't usually need to do this, since I'm
automating even more of my resource collection, but it's such a pain when I do.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Video Games"></category></entry><entry><title>Facade Was Underrated</title><link href="https:///facade-was-underrated.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2023-05-15T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2023-05-15T00:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Matteo Raso</name></author><id>tag:None,2023-05-15:/facade-was-underrated.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Yeah, it was definitely janky, but it's incredible that the devs were
able to make an AI that could respond to what the player says all the
way back in 2005. Another problem was that the devs were limited by
the number of lines that they could get the actors …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Yeah, it was definitely janky, but it's incredible that the devs were
able to make an AI that could respond to what the player says all the
way back in 2005. Another problem was that the devs were limited by
the number of lines that they could get the actors to record, so the
dialogue had to be constricted. It would be amazing if somebody tried
to make a spiritual sequel that uses audio deepfakes for voice acting
and some sort of LLM to handle the responses.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Video Games"></category></entry></feed>